Hey, kid!
هي به
Hey, Ismael. Catch!
هي اسماعيل بير
Such a pleasure to see you, Herr Lieberman.
قدر از ديدنتون خوشحالم آقاي ليبرمن
The pleasure is all mine, Herr Strasser, I assure you.
ديدار شما باعث سعادته آقاي استراسر من اطمينان ميدم
I hate to bother such a famous Nazi hunter, like yourself,
من از اينکه بابت کرايه ناقابل بخوام شکاري نازي مشهوري ون شما رو
with such trifle as the rent, but it is the third of the month.
رنجيده خاطر کنم متنفرم.اما خوب امروز سومين روز ماه هست
Quite so, you will have a cheque in several days.
کاملا صحيح ميفرماييد تا ند روز ديه يه ک بهتون ميدم
By all means, take your time, Herr Lieberman.
ميخوام بم که...صبر کن آقاي ليبرمن
Feel free to ignore your responsibilities,
راحت باش و اصلا به دلت بد راه نده
while my property is being ruined.
که شما مسوول از بين رفتن اموالم هستيد
We have floods all over the building, because of you.
تمام ساختمون رو آب رفته بخاطر شما
You overload the floor putting a strain on the pipes upstairs,
شما  با ذاشتن بار به روي لوله هاي بالاي له ها و ايجاد فشار
and then they break.
باعث شديد اونها بشکنن
The pipes upstairs break, and I'm to blame?
لوله هاي بالا شکسته شدن و اونوقت منو داري سرزنش ميکني؟
Everything is connected.
همه يز به هم ربط داره
The whole building will soon collapse because of you.
به زودي کل ساختمان به خاطر شما فرو مي ريزه
- Ezra! - Get out!
ازرا برو بيرون
- You have no right... - You have a call from Paraguay.
شما حق نداريد يه تماس از اراوئه داريد
This is an apartment house, not an office building.
اين يک آارتمان مسکونيه نه يک ساختمان اداري
You have no right to bring in these heavy cabbinets in here.
شما اجازه نداريد اين کابينتهاي سنين رو اينجا بياريد
All right, all right.
خيلي خوب...باشه
So next time rent to a feather merchant.
خوب دفعه بعد به يه تاجر ردن کلفت اجاره بده
Hello.
سلام
Mr. Lieberman?
آقاي ليبرمن؟
- Out! You understand! - You get out!
بيرون...فهميدي؟ برو بيرون
Go and fix your rotten plumbing.
برو و لوله هاي وسيدت رو تعمير کن
Barry Kohler? No, I don't think I know you.
بري کوهلر؟نه فکر نميکنم من شما رو ميشناسم
I sent you a package with photos.
يه بسته همراه با عکس واستون فرستادم
You didn't?
نرفتيد....؟
You sound like an American.
به نظر مياد آمريکايي باشي
What are you doing in Paraguay?
توي اراوئه ه کار ميکني؟
I've been monitoring the activities of a group of Nazis.
من دارم فعاليتهاي يك روه از نازيها رو زيرنظر مي يرم
And I've identify several of them as war criminals.
و تعداد زيادي از اونها رو به عنوان جنايتكارهاي جني شناسايي كردم
Well, from your books and articles.
خوبه.از  كتابها و داستانهاي خودت
Forty years of heartbreak and sacrifice and you call it junk!
هل سال قلبهاي شكسته و قرباني دادن رو بهش ميي آشغال
Yes, junk! Junk, junk!
آره.آشغال...آشغال...آشغال
Herr Strasser, we are wasting valuable time.
آقاي استراسر ما داريم وقت رانبها رو هدر ميديم
The hole up there is very enormous.
اون سوراخ كه اون بالاست خيلي بزره
Huge chunks of plaster are coming down from your ceiling.
تكه هاي بزر از  داره از سقف ميريزه ايين
Look, how I step on the ground.
ببين من طوري روي زمين ا ميذارم؟
Quite soon I will be through into your apartment,
هر لحظه ممكنه بيفتم توي آارتمان شما
right into the lap of your beloved wife. God forbid.
مستقيم ميفتم روي زن دوست داشتني شما. خدا رحم كنه
- Come. - Don't push me.
بيا منو هل نده
Leave my brother and me alone. Get out!
من و برادرم رو تنها بذار برو بيرون
Come, Herr Strasser.
بيايد آقاي استراسر
Esther, the man's an idiot.
استر،اون مرد احمقي بود
No, I'm an idiot for letting him make me angry.
نه...من احمق هستم كه اجازه دادم من رو عصباني كنه
- Go on, take your phone call. - Oh!
زود باش .تلفن رو جواب بده اوه
The young man who's just discovered there are Nazis in South America.
مرد جواني كه به تازي نازيها رو در آمريكاي جنوبي كشف كرده
So, Mr. Kohler, forgive the interruption.
خوب آقاي كهلر...از اينكه معطل شديد معذرت ميخوام
I work alone like you, Mr. Lieberman,
من هم مثل شما تنها كار ميكنم آقاي ليبرمن
which is why I'm calling you. You see, I'm onto something.
واسه همين من با شما تماس رفتم مي بينيد يه يزايي سرم ميشه
Mr. Kohler, it maybe a blinding revelation to you,
آقاي كوهلر ممكنه دار اختلال بينايي شده باشي
that there are Nazis in Paraguay,
كه ديدي نازيها در اراوئه هستن
but I assure you, it is no news to me.
ولي به شما اطمينان ميدم كه اين خبر صحت نداره
And if you stay there much longer, there will still be Naziss in Paraguay,
و اه شما بيشتر از اين اونجا بمونيد هنوز نازيها در اراوئه وجود خواهند داشت
but there will be one less Jewish boy in the world.
اما يك نفر از تعداد يهوديهاي جهان كم خواهد شد
Something's going on.
يه خبرايي داره ميشه
They seemed to be gathered for some kind of operation.
به نظر مياد واسه انجام يك عمليات دور هم جمع شدن
A bunch of them have been moving in and out of Ralph Gunther's estate.
يه تعداد از اونها به ملك رالف انتر وارد ميشن و خارج ميشن
I want to know what to do next.
من ميخوام بدونم بعدش بايستي ه كار كنيم
Get on a plane and go home, or better still go to the American Embassy,
سوار هوايما شو و برو خونه و بهتره كه بري سفارتخانه آمريكا
run to the American Embassy and tell them to put you on the plane.
برو به سفارتخانه آمريكا و ازشون بخواه كه تو رو سوار هوايما كنن
Thank you for your advice.
از نصيحت شما متشكرم
What did he want?
اون ي ميخواست؟
I don't know.
نميدونم
Advise, instructions.
نصيحت...دستورات
A boy like that. Lucky to survive one day in Paraguay!
سري مثل اون بايستي خيلي خوش شانس باشه كه بتونه يك روز در اراوئه زنده بمونه
He's been there some weeks.
اون ند هفته هست كه اونجاست
I told him to go home, anyhow.
به هر حال من بهش فتم بررده خونه
What does he want, applause?
اون دنبال ي هست؟تشويقي؟
One, two, three, four.
يك،دو،سه،هار
One, two.
يك،دو
- Goddamn, it works!
ايول كارميكنه داره كار ميكنه
Come on, damn you, tune in.
زود باش لعنتي تنظيم شو
Gentlemen, he's coming.
آقايون داره مياد
So, Gunther,
س،انتر
this is the moment.
اين همون لحظه هست
Gentlemen, gentlemen, be at your ease, I beg of you.
آقايون آقايون راحت باشيد خواهش ميكنم
- Gunther, would you do the honours? - Certainly, Dr. Mengele.
انتر ميشه لطفا معرفي كنيد؟حتما آقاي مينل
Mengele.
مينل
Captain Gerhart Mundt.
كايتان رهارد موند
Yes, yes, I have heard nothing but the highest praise for you, captain.
بله بله.من كه تا حالا اسمتون رو نشنيدم. ولي شما رو تحسين ميكنم
Thank you, Herr Doctor.
متشكرم دكتر
- Major Ludwig Trausteiner. - Thank you for coming, Major.
متخصص لودوي تراستينر ممنونم كه تشريف اورديد
- Captain... - All right, Gunther.
کايتان باشه انتر
Captain Farnbach and I are old comrades.
کايتان فارن باخ و من از دوستان قديمي هستيم
Are we not, captain?
مه نه کايتان؟
It is extremely flattering to be remembered after all those years, sir.
باعث افتخاره که بعد از اين همه سال در ياد شما موندم آقا
I am not so senile, or so ungrateful that I cannot remember a loyal officer
من هنوز خيلي ير و ناساس نيستم که يک افسر وفادار رو به ياد نيارم
from the early days of the struggle.
از اولين روزهاي کشمکش
And now for the youth.
و حالا براي جواني
This is Dietrich Hessen, son of Wilhelm Hessen.
ايشون ديتري حسن  فرزند ويلهلد حسن هستند
Welcome, young man.
خوش آمدي مرد جوان
- Wolfgang Kleist. - I am pleased you are with us.
ولف ن کليست خوشحالم که همراه ما هستيد
Thank you, Herr Doktor.
ممنونم دکتر
- And Otto Schwimmer. - A great pleasure, Herr Schwimmer.
و اوتو شويمر بسيار از آشناييتون خوشحالم آقاي شويمر
And now to business.
و حالا بريم سراغ کار
Sit down, gentlemen, please.
لطفا بشينيد آقايون
The task before you is the most important operation
وظيفه اي که به عهده شماست انجام يکي از مهمترين عملياتهايي  است که
that the Kamerades organization has ever undertaken.
تا به حال سازمان انجام داده
It is the vital link in a programme
اين يک يوند حيات هست طي يک برنامه
to which I and your leaders have devoted many years of huge effort.
به ساليان سال تلاش عظيم و جانساري
Your success on this project carries with it the hope
موفقيت شما در اين روژه اميد و سرنوشت
and destiny of the Aryan race.
نژاد آريايي را به همراه دارد
And that is not an exageration, but the literal truth.
و اين اغراق نيست بلکه حقيقت محض است
It is a holy mission, gentlemen.
اين يک ماموريت مقدسه آقايون
You should consider yourselves highly honoured
شما بايد به خودتان بسيار افتخار کنيد
to have been chosen to perform it.
که براي اجراي اين ماموريت اتخاب شده ايد
Now for the details.
حالا جزئيات
In the next two-an-half years, ninety-four men
در دو سال و نيم آينده 94 نفر بايد
must die on or near certain dates.
در تاريخهاي معين بميرند
Sixteen of these men are in West Germany,
که 16 نفر آنها در آلمان غربي هستند
fourteen in Sweden, thirteen in England,
و 14 نفرشون در سوئد و13 نفر در انليس هستند
twelve in the United States, ten in Norway,
و 12 نفر در آمريکا و 10 نفر در نروژ
nine in Austria, eight in Holland,
و 9 نفر در اتريش و 8 نفر در هلند
and six each in Denmark and Canada.
و 6 نفر باقيمانده در دانمارک و کانادا
A total of ninety-four
در مجموع 94
assassinations.
قتل
All of these men
تمام اين مردها
will be sixty-five years old when their dates come around.
بايد 65 ساله باشن وقتي زمانشون فرا ميرسه
Obviously, a few of them will already have died of natural causes.
مشخصه كه تعدادي از اونها تا به حال در اثر موارد طبيعي فوت كرده باشن
Yes, Farnbach.
آره فارنباخ
Who are these men? Jews?
اين مردها كي هستن؟ يهودي هستن؟
Not one.
نه هي كدوم
They are all family men, tax inspectors,
اونها همه مردهاي خانواده هستن بازرس مالياتي
civil servants, school principals, men of minor authority.
خدمتكارهاي غيرنظامي, مديران مدرسه, مرداني با اختيارات كوك
Are we permitted to hire accomplices?
آيا ما اجازه داريم كه دستيار داشته باشيم؟
Accomplices? I would not advise it.
دستيار؟ من كه توصيه نميكنم
Bear it in mind, these are sixty-five year old men.
به ياد داشته باشيد اونها مردهاي 65 ساله هستن
Their eyesight is failing, they have slow reflexes, diminished strength.
شماشون ضعيف شده.واكنشها كند شده و قدرتشون كاهش يدا كرده
I've been through Sweden quite a bit,
من يه مدت كمي توي سوئد بودم
but I've never heard of this place, Rasbo.
ولي هي وقت در موردش يزي نشنيدم راسبو
It is a village. About fifteen kilometres from Upsala.
اون يه روستا هست 15 كيلومتر بالاتر از آسالا
That is Bertile Hayden, the post master, there.
اون برتال هايدن هست اونجا .رئيس ست
And by killing this old mail man
و با كشتن اين يرمرد ستي
I will be fulfilling the destiny of the Aryan race?
من سرشار از سرنوشت نژاد آريايي مي شوم
You wish to be relieved of this assignment, captain Mundt?
تو دوست داري از اين انتقال قانوني  رها بشي آقاي ماندت
No, sir.
نه آقا
Then, do not question your orders.
س در مورد دستورات سوال نكن
Simply obey them.
به سادي ازشون اطاعت كن
Yes, Herr Doktor.
بله دكتر
I apologise.
من عذر ميخوام
Further questions?
سوال ديري هست؟
The men's families are not to be involved.
خانواده مردها توي اين قضيه نيستند
And in the case of say younger wives
و از طرفي همسران جواني
who might be open to romantic overtures as accomplices.
كه رابطه عاشقانه دارند به عنوان شريك جرم خواهند بود
I repeat, the families are not to be involved.
تكرار ميكنم.خانواده ها شامل اين قضيه نميشن
You will travel and live in a manner befitting
تو اون طوري كه برازنده خودت هست سفر ميكني و زندي ميكني
salesmen, for large German firms.
فروشنده ها براي تجارتخانه هاي بزر
You'll have more than enough money for any equipment you might need.
تو براي تمام تجهيزات مورد نيازت به اندازه كافي ول داري
It is vital that you check in with headquarters on the first...
حياتي هست كه توسط رئيسها ك بشيد در اول
Find it!
يداش كن
Sir!
آقا
All right, Mr. Lieberman, listen to this.
باشه آقاي ليبرمن به اين وش كن
Killing this old mail man,
كشتن اين يرمرد ستي
I will be fulfulling the destiny of the Aryan race?
من سرشار از سرنوشت نژاد آريايي خواهم شد؟
Operator, any word of my call yet?
اراتور تماس من برقرار نشد؟
Hello.
سلام
Kohler!
كهلر
I thought I told you to leave.
فكر كنم بهت فتم كه بري
Well, I didn't Mr. Lieberman, but I think you're going to be glad I didn't.
خوب من نرفتم و فكر ميكنم كه تو از اينكه من نميرم خوشحال هستي
Doktor Josef Mengele was here tonight.
دكتر جوزف مينل امشب اينجا بود
You mean to tell me you've called me up at 3 o'clock in the morning
منظورت اينه كه ساعت 3 صبح بامن تماس رفتي كه بي اون اينجاست
to tell me Doktor Josef Mengele is in Paraguay?
كه بي دكتر جوزف مينل در اراوئه هست
I know that, Mr. Kohler, so does my sister,
من اينو ميدونم آقاي كهلر خواهرم هم ميدونه
so does my landlord, and my tailor, and now you know it too.
صاحبخونه و خياط ما هم ميدونه و حالا شما هم ميدونيد
My congratulations!
تبريک ميم
He came to a meeting at Gunther's house tonight.
اون امشب توي يک جلسه در خانه انتر شرکت کرد
The others were there too.
بقيه هم اونجا بودن
Mengele's sending them out to kill ninety-four, sixty-five year old men
مينل داشت اونها رو واسه کشتن 94 مرد با سن 65 سال بيرون ميفرستاد
in the next two-an-half years.
که اين کار رو در 2سال و نيم آينده انجام بدن
What are you talking about?
ي داري ميي؟
Ninety-four at sixty-five...
نود و هارتا 65 ساله؟
two-an-half years.
دو سال و نيم
I can hear you, Mr. Kohler, I just can't follow what you're saying.
من صدات رو ميشنوم آقاي کهلر.فقط نميتونم بفهمم ي داري ميي
Goddamn it, you don't have to believe me, I've got it all on tape.
خدا لعنتش کنه.تو مجبور نيستي باورم کني من تمامش رو روي نوار ضبط کردم
All of them, Europe, Canada, the United States.
همشون اروايي کانادايي و آمريکايي هستند
Mostly civil servants.
اکثرا خدمتکارهاي غيرنظامي
Okay, I'm running it down now. It'll only take a second.
خوب دارم نوار رو برميردونم فقط ند ثانيه وقت شما رو مي يره
Take your time, old men don't go back to sleep once they've been awakened.
زمان واسه خودت.يرمردها تا زماني که اونها بيدارند نميرن واسه خواب
- Welcome, young man. - The stuff on now, it's just a lot of
خوش آمدي مرد جوان کارمون شروع ميشه
introducing and glad handing around.
تا الان فقط معرفي کرديم
Mengele is acting like chairman of the board.
مينل شبيه رئيس اونها برخورد ميکنه
Will you stop asking questions and just listen Mr. Lieberman?
ميشه اينقدر سوال نکني و فقط وش بدي آقاي ليبرمن؟
Okay, here it comes.
خوب اينجا رو داشته باش
The task before you is the most important...
وظيفه اي که شما داريد بسيار مهمه
Kohler!
کهلر
Are you there, Kohler?
تو اونجايي کهلر؟
... your success on this project...
موفقيت شما در اين روژه
Kohler.
کهلر
Clean the room.
اتاق رو تميز کنيد
Dispose of the body.
ترتيب جسد رو بديد
I do not want a trace of this vermin to remain.
نميخوام هي اثري از اين جانور موذي باقي بمونه
Everything is all right, you can take care of the police.
همه ي روبراهه تو حواست به ليس باشه
- Who was the boy calling? - It does not matter.
سره با کي تماس رفته بود اين مهم نيست
- Perhaps you should wait? - We wait for nothing,
شايد بايد صبر ميکردي نا منتظر يزي نيستيم
the fourth Reich is coming, Gunther.
ري هارم داره مياد انتر
Our men will leave tomorrow as planned.
مردهاي من فردا راه ميفتن طبق نقشه
Kill him.
بکشش
Is there no way of checking this further?
راه نداره بيشتر بررسي بشه؟
All right, thank you.
باشه متشکرم
The Vienna telephone exchange says there was a call from Paraguay,
شرکت ارتباطات وينا ميه تماس از اراوئه بوده
but Paraguay say that no such call took place.
اما اراوئه فته همين تماسي اصلا وجود نداشته
I have finally found a couple of things from that boy.
من بالاخره يه يزهايي از اين سره به دست آوردم
Mundt!
ماندت!
Captain in a Death-Head Regiment.
کايتان در راس روه مر
Farnbach, a Gestapo agent.
فارنباخ نماينده شتاو
Trausteiner! Assistant commandant, at Dachau.
ترستينر کمک فرمانده در داکائو
Cheap bureaucrats and murderers.
مامورين دولتي ست و قاتلها
And these...
و اينها
who knows.
کي ميدونه
- Ezra, you know, you shouldn't. - Esther, Esther,
ازرا تو ميدوني...تو نبايد استر...استر
after all I've been through, one puff won't hurt me.
بعد از اينهمه مدت يه فوت کويک نميتونه به من صدمه بزنه
These...
اينها
Colonel Eduard Seibert, he's the adjutant to Rausch,
سرهن ادوارد سايبرت ايشون کمک راش هستند
the head of the Kamerads organization.
رئيس سازمان کامراد
He was in command of the extermination units on the Eastern Front.
ايشون تحت فرماندهي واحد انهدام يشخوان شرقي بودند
He's a real aristocrat,
ايشون يک نجيب زاده واقعي هستند
what's he doing in such undistinguished company?
اون ه کاري ميکنه توي يک همين شرکت منامي؟
And then, it wasn't a hoax after all.
و به هر حال يک کلک نبود
Esther,
استر
on the telephone, after that boy was cut off,
توي اون تماس زماني که سره قطع کرد
I felt something...
من يه يزي حس کردم
something in the silence, something alive,
يه يزي توي سکوت,يه يز زنده
and...
و
hateful.
منفور
Maybe, I'm getting senile.
شايد من خرف شدم
You haven't got the time.
وقت زيادي نداري
Ninety-four... ordinary men.
نود و هار مرد معمولي
Beynon!
باينون
Oh, Christ!
اوه خداي من
Mr. Beynon, so nice to see you again.
آقاي باينون از اينکه دوباره مي بينمتون خوشحالم
- How are you getting along? - Can't complain, who'd listen.
طور داري اين اطراف مي ردي؟ نميشه از يه شنونده شکايت کرد
- May I take up a moment of your time? - I'm so sorry, I'm late for lunch.
ميشه ند لحظه از وقت شما رو بيرم؟ متاسفم دارم ميرم نهار بخورم.ديرم شده
Oh, always such a prodigious appetite.
اوه هميشه اشتهاي شفت انيزي داريد
What?
ي؟
Eight times last week I call you
هفته ذشته 8 مرتبه با شما تماس رفتم
and each time you are at lunch. Maybe you have a tate warm?
و هر دفعه شما در حال نهار خوردن بوديد شايد شما مشکل وارشي داريد
Now, Sidney, please, just a few moments of your time.
حالا سيدني...لطفا..فقط ند لحظه وقت شما رو مي يرم
Very well, come on.
خيلي خوب...بفرما
Ezra, you carry this whole damn concentration camp thing
ازرا تو همه اين لعنتيها رو
pinned to your coat-tails.
دنبال خودت ميکشوني
Why do you keep knocking yourself out?
را داري خودت رو به کشتن ميدي؟
Nothing ever pays off.
يزي هم که يرت نمياد
Frieda Maloney is in jail.
فرادا مالوني توي زندانه
Frieda Maloney! She was only a guard in a camp.
فرادا مالوني...اون فقط يک نهبان کم بود
She strangled young girls with their own hair,
اون دخترهاي جوان رو با موهاي خودشون خفه مي کرد
bayonetted infants. - Maybe she was a despicable criminal,
دخترهاي کويک رو مي کشت شايد اون يک جنايتکار ستي بوده
but she just isn't news thirty years later.
ولي تنها همين خبر نيست سي سال بعد
Sidney, there is a plot by the Kamerads Organization,
سيدني يک دسيسه توسط سازمان کامراد داره شکل مي يره
which is the illegal army...
که يک سازمان نظامي قانوني هست
Yes, I know what it is.
آره.ميدونم ي هستش
They plan to kill ninety-four men in the next two-an-half years.
اونها برنامه دارن که توي دو سال و نيم آينده 94 نفر رو بکشن
Jews, I suppose?
يهوديها.فکر کنم
I want your European, Canadian and American bureaus
من دفاتر اروا و کانادا و آمريکاي شما رو ميخوام
to send you clippings
که اخبار مربوط به تمام
of all sixty-five year old civil servants who die accidentally.
خدمتکاران غيرنظامي که تصادفا مرده اند رو واستون بفرستم
You pass them to me and I'll go through them.
تو اونها رو براي من ميفرستي و من هم در موردشون تحقيق ميکنم
And whose plot is this?
و اين نقشه مربوط به کي هست؟
Josef Mengele.
جوزف مينل
He's the red herring in this little barrel?
اون شاه ماهي قرمزي هست توي اين بشکه کوک
What a title for the chief doctor of Auschwitz
ه نام برازنده اي واسه رئيس دکتران آشويتز
who killed two-an-half million people,
که دو و نيم ميليون انسان رو کشته
experimented on children, Jewish and non-Jewish,
روي کودکان يهود و غير يهود آزمايش مي کرد
using twins mostly, injecting blue dyes into their eyes
بيشتر روي دوقلوها.رن آبي توي شمهاي به ها تزريق مي کرد تا اونها رو تبديل به
to make them acceptable Aryans.
نژاد آريايي قابل قبول بکنه
Ezra.
ازرا
Amputating limbs and organs from thousands,
اعضاي بدن و آلت هزاران نفر رو قطع مي کرد
operating without anaesthetic, but with the strenght of Wagner
جراحي بدون داروي بيهوشي اما با قدرت وانر
providing an obligato to the screams of the mutons he was creating.
با فراهم نمودن يک ضامن جهت اعمال وحشتناک خودش
Don't lecture me!
واسه من سخنراني نکن
Sidney,
سيدني
you owe me something.
تو يه يزي به من بدهکاري
Even if only to humour an old man
حتي ار براي خوشحالي يرمردي باشه
who once brought you page one international story.
که براي اولين بار صفحه اول داستانهاي بين المللي رو آورد
You owe me this much, Sidney.
تو اينقدر به من بدهکاري
Now, I'm collecting.
حالا من در حال جمع آوري هستم
Have you any idea how many men in their mid-sixties,
ميدوني روزانه ه تعداد مرد 60 ساله
die every day?
مي ميره؟
I try not to think about it.
تا حالا به اين فكر نكردم
Save it for your wife, Herr Doring.
اينو واسه زنت نه دار
What I've got is too good for her.
يزي كه من دارم خيلي واسش خوبه
I can feel that, Herr Doring.
ميتونم احساسش كنم
Go on, go on.
ادامه بده...ادامه بده
Pig.
خوك
Good boy.
سر خوب
Seibert!
سايبرت
News?
خبريه؟
Good news, our salesmen have all checked in.
خبر خوب.فروشنده هاي ما وارد شدن
The first quotas have been filled, all on the exact dates.
اولين سهميه ها ر شدند.دقيقا در تاريخهاي معين شده
Two a day early and one a day late.
دوتا در يک روز قبل و يکي در روز بعدش
Splendid, splendid! Come.
اسلنديد...اسلنديد...بيا
We'll have a nice lunch.
يه نهار خوبي ميخوريم
Colonel, I will need to have a full report on all this for my records.
سرهن من يک زارش کامل از تمام اينها ميخوام.واسه ثبت سابقه
I've already taken care of that.
من از قبل حواسم به اين موضوع بوده
Four out of seven on the exact dates.
هار تا از هفت تا در تاريخ معين
They are good men.
اونها مردهاي خوبي هستن
Well chosen.
خوب انتخاب شدند
General Rausch called me yesterday from the Costa Brava.
ژنرال راش ديروز از کاستا براوا با من تماس رفت
Why didn't you tell us about Lieberman?
را در مورد ليبرمن يزي به ما نفتي؟
I did not think this was necessary.
فکر نمي کردم ضرورتي داشته باشه
The General is concerned.
ژنرال ناراحت شده
But Ezra Lieberman, no one takes him seriously.
ولي ازرا ليبرمن رو کسي جدي نمي رفت
Even the rich Jews who used to send him money,
حتي يهوديهاي ولداري که واسش ول ميفرستادن
have found better ways to ease their consciences.
راه بهتري واسه آسوده کردن خيالشون يدا کردن
The man's bank has failed,
بانک اين بابا هم ورشکسته شد
his followers have fallen away from him.
طرفدارهاش اون رو رها کردند
He's entirely without credibility, I just decided he was not important.
او کاملا از اعتبار ساقط شد من هم تصميم رفتم ديه اهميتي بهش ندم
If you'll forgive me, Herr Doktor, it was not your decision to make.
با عرض معذرت آقاي دکتر ولي شما مجاز نبوديد که تصميم بيريد
You could have compromised their agents all over the world.
شما ميتونستيد با تمام نماينده هاش در سراسر دنيا مصالحه کنيد
And if I have told you about Lieberman,
و ار من در مورد ليبرمن به شما فتم
you would have compromised my project.
شما مي بايست با روژه من توافق مي کرديد
How bad would it be if we postponed for three or four months?
قدر بد ميشه ار ما سه يا هار ماه کارمون عقب بيفته
That would reduce the outcome by...
اين باعث ميشه که نتيجه 20 در صد
twenty percent, there are 18 men in the first four months
کاهش يدا کنه.در هار ماه اول ميشوند 18 مرد
it would change the results completely.
اين باعث ميشه نتيجه کاملا تغيير کنه
Assuming that there is an outcome.
با فرض بر اينکه نتيجه اي وجود داشته باشه
There'll be exactly the results I have promised.
دقيقا همان نتايجي که قول داده بودم وجود دارند
General Rausch wanted to recall these six men.
ژنرال راش ميخواد با اين 6 مرد دوباره تماس بيره
Impossible!
غيرممکنه
Until we find out how much Lieberman knows.
تا زماني که بفهميم ليبرمن قدر ميدونه
Impossible, this project has a timetable
غيرممکنه.روژه يک بازده زماني داره که
that muste be observed, it cannot be changed.
مي بايست در نظر رفته بشه نميشه اون رو تغيير داد
Herr Doktor...
آقاي دکتر
Colonel, do you fully understand what it is that I have done?
سرهن آيا شما کاملا متوجه شدي اون کاري که من کردم ه بود؟
I, the outlaw,
من...قانون شکني
the so-called war criminal.
که بهش مين جنايت جني
Right here in this God-forsaken place,
درست همينجا در اين مکان فراموش شده خدا
I have created a scientific miracle.
من يک معجزه علمي به وجود آوردم
I have turned the whole world into a laboratory.
من تمام جهان رو تبديل به آزمايشاه کردم
Our laboratory.
آزمايشاه ما
Don't talk me about six men.
بامن درباره 6 تا مرد صحبت نکن
I would send out six more if they were caught,
ار اونها رفته مي شدند من 6 تا ديه ميفرستادم
and six more, and six more, until the task was done.
و 6 تاي ديه...و 6 تاي ديه تا زماني که کار انجام بشه
I agree, Herr Doktor, I agree.
من موافقم دکتر...موافقم
I hope that we can resolve this Lieberman business,
اميدوارم بتونيم سر از قضيه ليبرمن در بياريم و
and that you get to put 94 check marks on that beautiful chart of yours.
و اينکه تو 94 تا علامت بر روي اون نمودار خوشکلت ذاشتي
Come.
بيا
Walk me to the plane.
با هم بريم سمت هوايما
You see how passionate I am on this subject.
ميدوني که من قدر روي اين موضوع احساساتي هستم
Uh huh!
اوه
To think that one day this place will be a shrine
فکر اينکه يه روزي قراره اين مکان تبديل بشه به زيارتاه و
to be visited by millions of school-children.
ميليونها به مدرسه اي ميان واسه ديدنش
Yes, that is a nice thought. Yes, Doktor.
آره اين فکر خوبيه...آره دکتر
Gladbeck, three-thirty, Ezra.
تعظيم سه هزارنفر ...ازرا
We'll get there, we'll get there, when do I ever miss a train?
ما ميريم اونجا....ما ميريم اونجا تا حالا کي شده که قطار رو از دست بدم؟
Now you know what to do while I'm away?
حالا ميدوني زماني که من نيستم ه کار بايد بکني؟
Go through all those clippings, separate them by countries, cities,
برو سراغ اخبارها و اونها رو بر اساس کشور و شهر جدا کن
try to isolate all violent crime.
سعي کن جنايات خشونت بار رو جدا کني
Ezra, there are already more than a hundred clippings
ازرا بيش از 100 خبر وجود داره
and Beynon called to say there are more to come.
و باينون تماس رفت که به تعداد بيشتري در راهه
Well, we have to start somewhere.
خوب ما بايد از يه جايي شروع کنيم
Yes, yes, but we can't afford to hunt for all those men.
آره..آره اما ما نميتونيم از عهده جستجوي اين همه آدم بر بيائيم
Well, that's why I'm going to these cities first,
خوب به همين دليل من اول دارم ميرم به اين شهرها
because they are the closest and the cheapest, it's the begining.
ون اينها از همه ارزونتر و نزديکتر هستن اين واسه شروعه
Yes, but you know that...
بله ولي شما ميدوني که
Remember to separate the ones in New England from the rest.
يادت باشه اونهايي رو که از نيو انلند هستن از بقيه جدا کني
I can cover them while I'm on the lecture tour.
من ميتونم اونها رو زماني که در سفر براي سخنراني هستم وشش بدم
Still, without any help.
هموز بدون کمک
Without help, without money, without time, what else is new?
بدون کمک بدون ول بدون زمان ديه ي جديد هست؟
The landlord!
صاحبخونه
Where are you going?
کجا داري ميري؟
- To turn that damn tape off. - Leave it, I like music.
ميخوام برم اون ضبط لعنتي رو خاموش کنم ولش کن.من از موزيک خوشم مياد
Well, he doesn't.
خوب او خوشش نمياد
He'll prowl round the landing listening at my door,
اون همين اطراف رسه ميزنه و از شت در اتاق من وش ميده
- just waiting to catch me. - Catch you? Doing what?
فقط منتظره منو بيره.تو رو بيره؟ ه کار کردي؟
Just what we're doing now, love.
فقط همين کاري که الان داريم مي کنيم عشق من
Mr. Harrington doesn't like any mucking-around in his house,
آقاي هارينتون دوست نداره هي هي اطراف اينجا رسه بزنه
he has a wife and kid, you know. Old coot!
اون زن وبه داره ميدوني ير خرفت
Bet he wouldn't say no if I invited him in here.
شرط مي بندم ار من دعوتش کنم اينجا نه نميه
Then maybe we'll invite him in.
س ممکنه ما دعوتش کنيم بياد
Later.
بعد
Is this Frau Doring's residence? My name is Lieberman.
اينجا محل اقامت فرا دورين هست؟ اسم من ليبرمن هست
Good.
خوبه
I think she's off the phone by now.
فکر ميکنم تلفنشون الان تموم شده باشه
You're her grandson?
شما نوه ايشون هستيد؟
Her son.
سرشون
Herr Lieberman!
آقاي ليبرمن
Frau Doring, thank you so much for seeing me.
فرا دورين.خيلي ممنون که منو ملاقات کرديد
Won't you sit down?
نميخواهيد بشينيد؟
Thank you.
ممنونم
You are the same man they had on television, several months ago.
تو همون مردي هستي که ند ماه يش آورده بودن به تلويزيون
The Nazi hunter. Frieda Maloney.
شکاري نازي فريدا مالوني
Do you kill Nazis when you catch them?
تو وقتي نازيها رو مي يري اونها رو ميکشي؟
That's against the law, it's much better to put them on trial
اين خلاف قانونه.خيلي بهتر از اينه که اونها رو محاکمه کنيد
- so people can learn. - Learn what?
س مردم ميتونن ياد بيرن ي رو ياد بيرن؟
Who they were, what they did.
که اونها که بودند و ه کردند
So why even catch them?
و را اونها رو رفتند
Just put it all in history books.
همه اينها رو توي کتابهاي تاريخ مينويسند
Clever boy you have here, Frau Doring.
سر باهوش اينجاداريم.فرا دارين
Yes, but definitely lazy.
آره...اما واقعا تنبل
For example, right now he should be in his room practising.
براي مثال اون الان بايد توي اتاقش در حال تمرين کردن باشه
I can't be in my room and answer the door at the same time, can I?
من که نميتونم به طور همزمان هم در رو باز کنم و هم توي اتاق خودم باشم.ميتونم؟
Oh! I was only teasing, darling.
اوه...من داشتم باهات شوخي مي کردم عزيزم
Now, please go and practise.
حالا لطفا برو و تمرين کن
Now we can talk.
حالا ميتونيم حرف بزنيم
First of all, may I express my sympathy,
اول از هر يز با شما ابراز همدردي ميکنم
things must be very difficult for you right now.
در حال حاضر شرايط براي شما خيلي سخت شده
Thank you.
ممنونم
Is he your only child?
اون تنها فرزند شماست؟
Yes.
بله
Did your husband leave all his money to Erich and you?
آيا شوهر شما تمام ثروتش رو براي شما و اريک ذاشت؟
And to a sister of his.
و خواهرش
Why do you ask that?
را اين رو ميرسيد؟
I was looking for a reason behind his death.
من دنبال يک انيزه براي قتل ايشون ميردم
Emil's death was an accident.
مر اميل يه تصادف بود
Was he a Nazi?
اون يه نازي بود؟
I did not meet him until 1955, so I have no way of knowing.
من تا سال 1955 اون رو نديده بودم س معلومه که نميدونستم
Did he ever mention the name of a Doktor Josef Mengele?
اون هي وقت اسمي از دکتر جوزف مينل نبرده بود؟
Who?
کي؟
There was a considerable age difference between you two.
شما دو تا اختلاف سني زيادي با هم داشتيد
That wasn't the only difference.
اين تنها تفاوت نبود
I was twenty, straight off the farm
من 20 سالم بود و از يه مزرعه کشاورزي اومده بودم
and he was Mr. High-an-Mighty of the Transport Commission.
و اون يه آدم کله نده در حمل و نقل بود
Forty-three, I think he was.
هل و سه سال داشت.فکر ميکنم
- Did he have any hobbies? - No.
آيا سررميهايي داشت؟ نه
Yes.
آره
Yes, he did have one special hobby, Herr Lieberman.
آره اون يه سررمي ويژه داشت آقاي ليبرمن
He humiliated and beat my son at every given opportunity.
از هر فرصتي براي تحقير کردن و کتک زدن سر کويک من استفاده مي کرد
Would you like me to tell you who really killed him?
ميخواهيد بدونيد در حقيقت ه کسي اون رو کشت؟
God.
خدا
To set free a stupid little farm girl after twenty-two years of unhappiness.
که به يه دختر احمق کشاورز بعد از 22 سال عذاب کشيدن آزادي ببخشه
Do Nazis answer prayers, Herr Lieberman?
آيا نازيها جواب دعا رو ميدن آقاي ليبرمن؟
No.
نه
That is God's business.
خدا اين کار رو ميتونه بکنه
And I have thanked him every night,
و من هر شب شکر زاري ميکنم
since he pushed Emil under that car.
ار زماني که او اميل رو زير ماشين انداخت
He could have done it sooner.
ميتونست اين کار رو زودتر بکنه
But I thank him anyway.
ولي به هر حال من اون رو شکر ميکنم
Who the hell are you?
تو ه خري هستي؟
Come in, Mr. Harrington. She wants to talk to you.
بيايد داخل آقاي هارينتون او ميخواد با شما حرف بزنه
I'll talk to her.
باهاش صحبت ميکنم
That would be nice.
اينطور خوبه
John!
جان
Simon, stop playing with those puppets and go and wash your hands for tea.
سايمون اينقدر با اين عروسکها ور نرو برو دستهات رو بشور واسه ايي
- Hallo. - I'm on my way, mother.
سلام من توي راهم مادر
If you'll hold on, I'll just get her.
ار منتظر بمونيد اون رو صدا ميزنم
Nancy!
نانسي
Nancy! Telephone, Nancy.
نانسي تلفن...نانسي
Come on, Nancy, you can't spend your life in bed.
زود باش نانسي نميشه که تمام عمرت تو رختخواب بموني
Nancy!
نانسي
Good, good, incredibly precise.
خوبه...خوبه...به طور باور نکردني دقيق
Everything right on schedule.
همه يز درست طبق برنامه
You didn't have to make the trip, Seibert, you could have used the radio.
نيازي نبود که سفر کني سايبرت ميتونستي از راديو استفاده کني
Not that I do not welcome a little intelligent company down here.
نه اونجوري که به شرکت کويک خوش آمد نم
Gunther remembered the digital clock you admired so much
انتر اون ساعت ديجيتال رو يادش هست که شما سنديده بودي
in his home.
توي خونه اش
Well, thank you, my friend.
خوب ممنون دوست من
Very nice of you.
نظر لطف شماست
Such a rational device.
ه وسيله عقلاني
- Remarkable. - There is a problem.
جالب توجه يه مشکلي هست
Lieberman.
ليبرمن
He was in Gladbeck, in Doring's house.
اون در لادبک هست در خونه دورين
Possibly he found out about Doring.
ممکنه در مورد دورين فهميده باشه
You don't know?
تو نميدوني؟
How could I?
طوري ميتونستم؟
- The boy, Kohler? - Impossible.
سره کهلر؟ غيرممکنه
Then, how did Lieberman get to Doring?
س ليبرمن طوري دورين رو يدا کرد؟
Sheer coincidence.
يه راست با هم برخورد کردند
That's not a very scientific explanation, is it, Doktor?
اين يک توضيح علمي نيست مه نه دکتر؟
Are you interrogating me, colonel Seibert?
شما داريد من رو بازجويي مي کنيد سرهن سايبرت؟
General Rausch put me in charge of security for this project.
ژنرال راش من رو به عنوان حراست اين روژه انتخاب کردند
How can I function, if I don't have all the facts?
طور ميتونم کارم رو بکنم ار حقيقت رو ندونم؟
But you do!
ولي شما ميدونيد
A nosey, incompetent, old Jew has bumbled onto one victim,
يه فضول,بي کفايت,يهودي ير يه قرباني رو سر هم کرده
what more do you have to know?
ه يز بيشتري بايد بدونيد؟
Any idiot could see the next logical step. Kill him!
هر ابلهي ميدونه که قدم بعدي يه.بکشيدش
We don't want to create a martyr.
ما نميخواهيم يک کشته ديه بوجود بياريم
Ridiculous!
مسخره هست
Besides, he could have contacted various police agencies,
اون ميتونسته با اداره ليس و يا آاهي
or intelligence services.
تماس رفته باشه
They would not pay any attention to him.
اونها زياد بهش اهميت نميدن
If he died suddenly, they would.
ار ناهان کشته بشه اهميت ميدن
Well.
خوب
Then, what are you going to do?
س حالا قصد داري ه کار کني؟
Lieberman will have to be watched more carefully from now on.
از حالا به بعد ليبرمن بايد با دقت بيشتري تحت نظر باشه
If he seems to be getting closer to us, a decision will be made.
ار ديديم که داره به ما نزديکتر ميشه اونوقت يه تصميم ديري مي يريم
We will balance the danger of killing Lieberman
بايد خطرکشتن ليبرمن رو در نظر داشته باشيم
against the scientific validity of your project.
در برابر صحت علمي روژه شما
Are you, my esteemed Chief of Security
آيا تو به عنوان رئيس مشهور حراست من
telling me that a project twenty years and millions of dollars in the making,
داري به من ميي که يک روژه 20 ساله با ميليونها دلار هزينه
will be dropped because of this insignificant impudent, old Jew?
قراره به خاطر يک يرمرد يهودي ستاخ بي ارزش از بين بره؟
It wouldn't do to antagonize me, Doktor Mengele.
اون نميتونه با من دشمني کنه دکتر مينل
I've been one of your few supporters,
من يکي از معدود حاميان شما بودم
since this Lieberman business began.
از زماني که سرو کله اين ليبرمن يدا شد
And should I drop to my knees in gratitude?
س ميخواي واسه قدرداني زانو بزنم؟
Listen to me, Seibert,
به من وش کن سايبرت
I will not permit you to lay your failure, or your fear at my door.
من به تو اجازه نميدم که شکست و يا ترس خودت رو در خونه من بندازي
I am a scientist, I have done my job.
من يه دانشمندم.کارم رو انجام داده ام
You are an executioner!
تو يک جلاد هستي
Do yours!
کار خودت رو بکن
Ezra!
ازرا
Oh! A reception committee.
اوه يه جلسه ذيرايي
How nice.
ه خوب
So, how did it go?
طور يش مي رفت؟
A very rewarding trip.
يه سفر فوق العاده
The Krassner death at Freiburn
مر کراسنر در فريبورن
was a genuine accident witnessed by many people.
يک حادثه واقعي بود که خيلي از مردم شاهد اون بودند
At Gladbeck, I met a young housewife
در لادبک من يه زن خانه دار جوان رو ديدم
who was not exactly heart broken by the death of her old husband.
که زياد از مر شوهر يرش دل شکسته نشده بود
And at Prozheim they slammed the door in my face.
و در روژيم اونها در رو به صورت من کوبيدن
That's the way it will probably be with most of these people.
در مورد اکثر مردم اينجا به همين شکل هست
- I know, come, let's get a coffee. - Yes, please.
ميدونم...بيا...بيا يه قهوه بخوريم بله لطفا
Excuse me, Mr. Lieberman?
ببخشيد آقاي ليبرمن؟
My name is David Bennett.
اسم من ديويد بنت هست
I think you know a friend of mine, Barry Kohler.
فکر کنم شما يکي از دوستان من به اسم بري کهلر رو بشناسيد
- Are you the boy who's been calling? - What news of Mr. Kohler?
تو همون سره هستي که تماس مي رفت؟ از آقاي کهلر ه خبر؟
None.
هيي
- I know he was working with you. - That's not correct.
من ميدونم که اون با شما کار مي کرد نه اين درست نيست
- Well, he was in contact with you. - How do you know that?
خوب اون با شما در تماس بود شما اين رو از کجا ميدونيد؟
- From letters we received. - We?
از نامه هايي که ما دريافت مي کرديم ما؟
The Young Jewish Defenders.
جوانان مدافع يهودي
They're a bunch of fanatics. Kohler told me he worked alone.
اونها يه روه متعصب هستند کهلر به من فت که تنها کار ميکنه
Yes, and he did, thanks to you.
آره تنها کار ميکرد....به لطف شما
After he read all your books, he decided to change his methods.
وقتي که تمام کتابهاي شما رو خوند تصميم رفت روش خودش رو عوض کنه
I did not send your friend to Paraguay.
من دوست شما رو به اراوئه نفرستادم
He sent me these.
او اين يزها رو واسه من فرستاد
To prove that he wasn't off on some wild goose-chase.
و ثابت ميکنه او واسه تعطيلات نرفته بود شکار غازهاي وحشي
He couldn't identify these three young guys, so I traced them.
او نميتونست 3 تا مرد جوان رو شناسابب کنه من هم اونها رو ترسيم کردم
This is Kleist, Hessen, this is Schwimmer,
اين كليست هست حسن شومر
members of a neo-Nazi organization in Paraguay.
اعضاي سازمان نئونازي در اراوئه
This has nothing to do with me.
اين به من ربطي نداره
Does Barry Kohler's life have anything to do with you?
آيا زندي بري كهلر به تو مربوط ميشه؟
- You have no right to talk that way. - Is Barry Kohler still alive?
تو حق نداري اينطوري صحبت كني بري كهلر هنوز زنده هست؟
- How do I know? - Mr. Lieberman, Barry is dead.
من از كجا بدونم؟ آقاي ليبرمن بري مرده
You know that.
شما ميدوني
And I know that. And that's why I'm here.
و من هم ميدونم من به همين دليل اينجام
To pick up where he left off.
كه بفهمم از كجا ناديد شد
That means with you.
واسه شما معني داره
I work alone.
من تنها كار ميكنم
Im' not asking you for a job,
من كه از شما تقاضاي كار نكردم
I simply want some information from you.
من يه مقدار اطلاعات ساده از شما ميخوام
I can't help you.
من نميتونم كمكي كنم
I won't leave you until you talk to me.
تا زماني كه با من حرف نزني از اينجا نميرم
I'm going to plant myself on your doostep,
من ميخوام خودم رو همينجا جلوي ادري بكارم
and I'll be waiting for you there every morning.
و هر روز صبح منتظرت ميمونم
You're stuck with me, until you give me the information that I need.
من بهت ميسبم تا زماني كه اطلاعاتي كه ميخوام رو بهم بدي
Ezra,
ازرا
I got another envelope of clippings from Beynon.
من يه نامه ديه در مورد خبر از باينون دستم رسيده
A big one.
يه بزرش
All right, young man.
خوب مرد جوان
We'll talk.
صحبت مي كنيم
Good morning.
صبح بخير
I'm looking for the village of Storein.
من دنبال روستاي استورين ميردم
You're going the wrong way.
تو مسير رو اشتباه داري ميري
Turn around and take the south road for about sixteen kilometres,
بررد و جاده جنوب رو بير و 16 كيلومتر برو
then bear right, you can't miss it.
بعد بي راست..مش نميكني
- Thanks. - What are you doing in these parts?
ممنون تو اين طرفها ه ميكني؟
- What? - You are not Swedish.
ي؟ تو كه سوئدي نيستي
I come from Don'tmund originally, but,
من اصالتا از دونتموند هستم ولي
I live in Stockholm now.
الان در استكهلم زندي ميكنم
I have spent some time in Germany myself.
من يه مدتي در آلمان بودم
Come now, Mundt! What's happened to your memory?
بيا ماندنت ه بلايي سر حافظه ات اومده؟
My God! Major Hartung!
خداي من هارتون
I knew it was you!
ميدونستم كه تو بودي
Can't I believe it! What in the world are you doing up here?
باورم نميشه...دنيا طور شده كه تو سر از اينجا در آوردي؟
Well, it's no great story, my sister was married to a Swede.
خوب زياد هم عجيب نيست.خواهرم با يك سوئدي ازدواج كرده
And after I escaped from the internment camp, I hid out with them.
و بعد از اينكه از كم نهداري فرار كردم رفتم و يش اونها قايم شدم
I am Lars Lofquist now, Inspector of the Power Company.
من لارف لوفكويست هستم.بازرس شركت نيرو
And now what about you?
و حالا شما طور؟
I came up here on a job, for the Comrades Organization.
من واسه يه كاري اينجا اومدم براي سازمان كامراد
In Sweden?
در سوئد؟
My God, what's going on?
خداي من داره ه خبر ميشه؟
Can you tell me or would it violate orders?
ميتوني بهم بي يا اين هم سريي از دستوره؟
What the hell with orders, I'm sick of orders.
دستورات ه كوفتي هستند؟ من از دستورات حالم به هم ميخوره
I'm up here in Storein to kill a school-teacher, on Saturday.
من اينجا در استورين هستم كه يه معلم به ها رو روز شنبه بكشم
But don't ask me why, I cannot make head or tail of it.
ولي ازم نرس را.من نه سر يازم نه ته ياز
Who is this teacher? Lundberg? Olafsson?
اين معلمه كي هست؟ لوندبر؟اولافسون؟
Lundberg.
لوندبر
But I don't know what he looks like.
ولي نميدونم شبيه ي هست
No doubt, he's probably a harmless old man, it doesn't make any sense!
شك نكن كه احتمالا يه يرمرد بي ضرره اون اصلا احساس نداره
It makes sense to your superiors
اين براي مافوقهات احساس داره
or they wouldn't have given you the assignment.
يا شايد هم سندي به شما ندادن
An order is an order.
دستور دستوره
Good God, man! You are an officer of the S. S!
خداي خوب...تو يك افسر اس اس هستي؟
Have you forgotten?
فراموش كرده اي؟
My honour is loyalty.
شرف من وفاداريم هست
Those words were supposed to be engraved on your soul.
اين كلمات قراره به همراه روحت توي قبر بروند
I know Lundberg.
من لاندبر رو ميشناسم
I will point him out to you.
من بهت نشونش ميدم
It isn't Lundberg.
اون لاندبر نيست
And it doesn't have to be Saturday.
و قرار نيست روز شنبه باشه
No one would have wanted to kill Jack.
هي كسي دوست نداره كه جك رو بكشه
The man was beloved.
مرد دوست داشتني هست
If you had seen the wreaths his students sent...
ار دسته لهايي كه دانش آموزاش فرستادن رو مي ديدي
I have only one or two more questions to ask.
من فقط يكي دوتا سوال ديه دارم كه برسم
Did your husband belong to any international group?
آيا شوهر شما به روه بين المللي وابسته بود؟
He was in the American Legion.
او توي هن آمريكا بود
Rotary.
رخشي
I guess that's international.
فكر ميكنم بين المللي باشه
The Legion sent a Colour Guard to the funeral.
هن يه لاکارد رني واسه مراسمش فرستاد
The coffin was drapped in the American flag.
دور تابوت رم آمريكا وشانده بودن
What are you doing out of bed?
تو بيرون از رختخواب ه ميكني؟
I just came to get a glass of grapefruit juice.
من فقط اومدم يه ليوان آب انور بخورم
He's got the flu, also I thought he could stay home a few days because of it.
اون سرما خورده فكر ميكنم بهتر باشه ند روزي توي خونه بمونه
This is Jack Curry Jr.
اين جك كاري هست
Just Jack Curry, now.
جك كاري
Jack, you bite your tongue. This is Mr. Lieberman.
جك زبونت رو از رفتي اين آقاي ليبرمن هست
A famous man from Vienna in Austria.
مرد مشهوري از وين در اتريش
- What's he famous for? - This is fantastic!
اون واسه ي مشهوره؟ عاليه
You know you have a double.
ميدونستي تو يك جفت داري؟
A boy who lives in Gladbeck in Germany, exactly like you.
يه سري توي لادبك آلمان زندي ميكنه كه درست شبيه تو هست
Exactly like me?
درست شبيه من؟
I never saw anything like it.
من تا به حال يزي شبيه اين نديدم
Two twin brothers could not be more the same.
دو تا برادر دوقلو بيشتر از اين نميتونن شبيه باشن
Jack, you go up to bed, and I'll bring you the juice.
جك برو بالا واسه خواب من آبميوت رو ميارم
- I want to find out about... - You do what I tell you!
من ميخوام در مورد اون كاري رو كه فتم انجام بده
When you start paying the doctor bills, then you can hang around
وقتي كه تونستي هزينه دكترها رو بدي اونوقت ميتوني اين اطراف برخي
and get sick all you want, now just say goodbye and go.
و سرما بخوري.حالا خداحافظي كن و برو بخواب
Jesus Christ! Goodbye.
خدايا خداحافظ
You watch your mouth, young man!
تو مراقب حرف زدنت باش مرد جوان
It's amazing!
اين حيرت آوره
I thought he was this young boy from Germany
فكر كردم همون سر جوان از آلمان هست
come to visit you.
كه اومده تو رو ببينه
Even the voice, the look in the eyes. Exactly.
حتي صدا و ناه شمهاش دقيقا
Look, I don't want to be rude, but as you can see, I got a lot of things to do.
ببين قصد جسارت ندارم اما همانطوري كه مي بينيد كارهاي زيادي دارم
Look, I'm sure that nobody shot Big Jack on purpose.
ببين من مطمئنم كه هي كس جك بزر رو از عمد نزده
It was a horrible accident.
اون يك تصادف وحشتناك بود
If you'll excuse me.
ار منو ببخشيد
Hello, is this the Harrington residence?
سلام.اينجا محل اقامت آقاي هرينتون هست؟
Yes, this is the Harrington residence.
بله اينجا محل اقامت هرينتون هست
Can I talk to your mother, please?
ميتونم با مادرتون صحبت كنم لطفا؟
Well, you could, but you can't.
خوب...ميتونستيد...ولي نميتونيد
This will only take a moment, I promise you.
فقط ند لحظه طول ميكشه قول ميدم
My mother isn't receiving today.
مادرم امروز كسي رونمي بينه
Well, perhaps if you told her that I...
خوب شايد ار شما بهش بيد كه
Don't you understand English, you ass?
شما انليسي نميفهمي عوضي؟
We are not at home.
ما توي خونه نيستيم
Wilcox had two married daughters.
ويلكاكس دو تا دختر ازدواج كرده داره
No, no sons.
نه... سر نداره
The Harringstons, do they have any children?
هرينتونها آيا به دارند؟
What did the boy look like?
سره ه شكليه؟
Sort of pale, he had straight dark hair, very dark,
كمي رن ريده موهاي تيره وصاف داره خيلي تيره
blue eyes.
شمان آبي
Yeah, yeah, I'm listening.
آره...آره...دارم وش ميدم
Why do you want to know about the kids all of a sudden?
شما ي ميخواهيد در مورد تمام اين به ها بدونيد؟
Listen, Mr. Bennett,
وش كنيد آقاي بنت
if you want to ask the questions, you pay for the phone call.
ار شما ميخواهيد سوال برسيد بايد هزينه تماس رو رداخت كنيد
No,
نه
nothing.
هيي
No, I haven't found a link.
نه...من يه ارتباط يدا نكردم
No, I'm in the dark.
نه...من توي تاريكي هستم
Yeah, I'll call you tomorrow, I promise.
آره.فردا با شما تماس مي يرم قول ميدم
I have to speak to you, Mr. Lieberman.
من بايد با شما صحبت كنم آقاي ليبرمن
Well, come in. I was just coming to see you.
خوب...بفرماييد.من تازه داشتم براي ديدن شما ميومدم
- Sit down. - No, I can't stay long.
بشين نه من نميتونم زياد بمونم
Jack Jr. Doesn't know where I've gone.
جك نميدونه كه من كجا رفته ام
Mr. Lieberman,
آقاي ليبرمن
my son is the only thing I've got.
سرم تنها يزي هست كه من دارم
- You can't take him away from me. - I have no intention of...
شما نميتونيد اون رو از من بيريد من هي تنشي در اين مورد
When you spoke about that boy in Germany, I got worried.
زماني كه شما در مورد اون سره در آلمان صحبت كردي من نران شدم
The lady who gave Jack Jr. To us, made us swear never to tell anyone.
زني كه جك رو به ما داد ما رو قسم داد كه در اين مورد به كسي يزي نيم
- Your son's adopted? - It's just that... she was a German lady.
اين سر رو به فرزندي رفته ايد؟ اين فقط...........اون يه زن آلماني بود
She was very nice, really.
اون زن واقعا خوبي بود
I was amazed when I read in the papers,
وقتي توي روزنامه در مورد اون کارهايي
about all the things you said she did.
که شما فتيد انجام داده خوندم تعجب کردم
Frieda Maloney.
فريدا مالوني
Oh, God!
اوه خدايا
I knew I should never have come here.
ميدونستم که هي وقت نبايد اينجا ميومدم
Will you give me your word that you do not have
ميشه به من اطمينان بديد که
any recording device in your briefcase?
هي وسيله ضبط کننده اي توي مدونتون نداريد؟
Thank you.
ممنونم
Do you have the depositions?
شما بره ها رو آورديد؟
I have brought one.
يکي رو آوردم
The agreement was that you would provide an advance look
توافقنامه اين بود که شما ناه يشرفته اي بر
at all the testimonies against my client.
تمام شواهدي که بر عليه موکل من هست داشته باشي
With particular regard to any scars, deformities, or disabilities,
با ناهي ويژه به تمامي زخمها,شکستيها و ناتوانيها
suffered by the witnessses.
شکنجه توسط شاهدين
Here. The deposition is brought in good faith.
اينجا.واهي با ايمان کامل آورده شده
Two others will come if the interview should prove satisfactory.
بقيه هم مي آيند ار مصاحبه رضايتبخش باشد
You realise how unjust all this is.
شما مي دانيد که تمام اينها بي عدالتيه
Mrs. Maloney has been married to an American citizen for 27 years.
خانم مالوني به مدت 25سال با يک شهروند آمريکايي ازدواج کرده بود
She has two children, one grandchild.
اون دو تا به داره و يک نوه
I suppose this can be...
من فکر مي کردم ميشه
corroborated?
تاييد شده؟
By the mother of the child and three other surviving witnesses.
توسط مادر به و سه تا شاهد زنده
You will keep the interview brief.
تو بايد مصاحبه رو کوتاه کني
You will discuss only my client's activities in America
شما فقط در مورد فعاليتهاي موکل من در آمريکا بحث ميکني
between 1964 and '67.
بين سالهاي 1964 تا 1967
You will ask nothing about the charges against her
يزي در مورد اتهامات عليه اون ازش نميرسي
or about any event that ocurred during, or directly after the war.
يا در خصوص حوادثي که در زمان جن و يا بعدش رخ داد
One question of that nature and I will immediately terminate the interview.
فقط يک دونه از اين سوالات برسي بلافاصله مصاحبه رو تمام ميکنم
So.
خوب
I am to speak to you about my work with the adoption agency.
من ميخوام با شما در مورد کارم با سازمان کودکان بي سررست صحبت کنم
- That is correct. - I don't mind.
درسته براي من مهم نيست که
What I did may have been slightly illegal, but,
کاري که من انجام دادم يه کمي غيرقانوني بود...ولي
I brought happiness to so many people and that's was important, huh?
من خوشحالي رو واسه خيلي از مردم آوردم و همين مهم هست
Now tell me, if you will,
حالا ار ميشه به من بيد
how you came to work for this agency?
طور شد كه اومدي واسه آژانس كار كني؟
In the spring of 1963 I was contacted by someone
بهار 1963 يه نفر با من تماس رفت
I knew in the Comrades Organization.
كه ميدونم از سازمان كامراد بود
Who?
كي؟
Frau Maloney will not answer that.
فرا مالوني به اين سوال جواب نميده
They helped me after the war
اونها بعد از جن به من كمك كردند
and wanted me to return the favour
و از من خواستن دوباره برردم
by getting a job in an adoption agency.
و يه شغلي توي آژانس كودكان بي سررست به من يشنهاد كردن
Did they say why?
اونها علتش رو فتند ؟
If you let me finish, you'll find out.
اه اجازه بدي حرفم تموم بشه متوجه ميشي
The Rush-Gaddis agency hired me.
آژانس راش اديس منو استخدام كرد
The Comrades Organization was interested in rejects.
سازمان كامراد علاقه به رد کردن داشت
Couples who had been denied children, because the husband was too old.
زوجهايي که فرزندانشون رو به دليل کهولت سن شوهر نمي ذيرفتند
I was to go through the files looking for applications,
من بايد در بين رونده ها دنبال مواردي مي شتم
specifically those of families with Nordic-Christian backgrounds,
خصوصا خانواده هايي با يشينه نوردين کريستين
in which the husband was born between 1910 and 1914
اونهايي که شوهر متولد بين سالهاي 1910 تا 1914 بود
and the wife between 1933 and 1937.
و زن بين 1933 تا 1937 بود
The husband had to have a job in something like civil service
شوهره مي بايست يه شغلي توي اداره اي مثل خدمات عمراني مي داشت
and both spouses had to be in perfect physical health.
و زن و شوهر بايد هر دو داراي فيزيک بدني سالم مي بودن
Did they say why they wanted all this?
اونها مي فتند که همه اين يزها واسه يه؟
That information is not relevant.
اين اطلاعات به درد نميخوره
I was expected to obey my orders, not to question them.
از من انتظار داشتند که دستورات رو اطاعت کنم نه اينکه سوال کنم
This I did. As I always had.
اين کاري بود که هميشه مي کردم
About a year after that I was ordered to contact
حدود يک سال بعد از من خواستند که با
several of the applicants and offer them a healthy white baby boy,
ند تا از خانواده ها تماس بيرم و يشنهاد يک به سفيد کوولو رو به اونها بدم
complete with New York State adoption papers.
بره هاي مربوطه توسط دولت در نيويورک تاييد ميشد
They were to pay me five hundred dollars
اونها بايد به من 500 دلار مي دادند
and after their medical certificates had been cleared,
و زماني که واهيهاي زشکي آماده مي شد
they would receive the babies.
اونها به رو تحويل مي رفتند
We would meet at a motel near Kennedy Airport,
ما در يک هتل کنار فروداه کندي ملاقات مي کرديم
The babies were delivered to me
به ها به من تحويل داده شده بود
usually by stewardesses with Varig Airlines.
معمولا توسط خدمه  هوايمايي واري
Varig?
واري؟
Did the babies all come from Brazil?
آيا تمام به ها از برزيل آورده مي شدند؟
- Is that important to you? - No.
اين واستون مهمه؟ نه
What did they look like?
اونها ه شکلي بودن؟
They were all beautiful little boys,
اونها همشون سربه هاي زيبايي بودن
black hair, piercing blue eyes.
موهاي مشکي و شمان آبي ريز
If you're looking for a long lost Jewish grandson, he was not among them.
اه داريد دنبال نوه يهودي م شده خودتون مي رديد بين اونها نبود
How many couples did you give the babies to?
به ند تا خانواده به ها رو تحويل مي دادي؟
About twenty.
تقريبا 20 تا
Only Americans?
فقط  آمريکايي؟
- Some were Canadian. - No Europeans?
يه تعداد کانادايي بودن اروايي هم بودن؟
No.
نه
Can you remember a Curry family?
خانواده اي به اسم کري يادته؟
- Curry? Yes. - Who else?
کري؟آره ديه کي؟
Wheelock.
ويلاک
Henry Wheelock.
هانري ويلاک
He gave me my dog Schatzie.
او س من شاتزي رو به من داد
Beautiful Doberman.
دوبرمن زيبا
It was only ten weeks old when I got him.
زماني که اون رو رفتم فقط 10 هفته سن داشت
Where is Wheelock from?
ويلاک اهل کجاست؟
New Providence, Pennsylvania.
رو ويدنس جديد...نسيلوانيا
And how long after the Currys,
خانواده ويلاک ه مدت بعد از خانواده
did the Wheelocks get their baby?
کري بشون رو دريافت کردند؟
That's fourteen years ago, I don't remember.
اين مربوط به 14 سال يشه يادم نمياد
And what has Josef Mengele to do with all this?
جوفز مينل با همه اينها ه کار بايد مي کرده؟
We won't answer that.
ما اين رو جواب نمي ديم
It was all a trick, wasn't it?
تمام ايتها يه حقه بود...درسته؟
I know nothing of Mengele,
من درباره مينل يزي نميدونم
but you'll link me with him, won't you?
ولي تو من رو به اون ربط ميدي. مه نه؟
You want your pound of flesh, you don't care how yuo get it!
شما جنايتکار حيوان رو ميخواهيد اهميت هم نمي ديد طوري بدستش بياريد
Thirty years! The world has forgotten!
سي سال جهان هم فراموش شده
Nobody cares!
کسي اهميت نميده
And you persist! And persist!
و شما همش اصرار مي کنيد و افشاري مي کنيد
Now, why don't you get off my back?
حالا را دست از سر من برنمي داريد؟
- One more minor question. - I'll say nothing to you.
يه سوال کوک ديه من ديه جواب نميدم
As you wish.
هر جور راحتي
This interview has not gone by any means to my satisfaction
اين مصاحبه واسه من راضي کننده نبود
I will therefore withold the other two depositions we talked about.
س ما سراغ دو تا شاهد ديه که فتيم ميريم
You lying Jewish schwein!
تو يه يهودي دروغويي
You're not a guard now, Madame!
خانم... شما الان نهبان نيستيد
You are a prisoner!
شما يک زنداني هستيد
I may leave here empty-handed,
ممکنه من از اينجا دست خالي برم
but you
ولي تو
are not going anywhere.
هي جايي نميري
I think Frau Maloney could answer one more question.
فکر کنم فرا مالوني مي تونست يه سوال ديه جواب بده
When is your dog's birthday?
تولد س شما ه روزيه؟
You are an insane old man after all, aren't you?
تو يک يرمرد ديوونه هستي....مه نه؟
Schatzie's birthday? It was December eleventh.
تولد شاتزي؟ تولدش 11 دسامبر بود
Have a safe trip, David.
سفر امني داشته باشي ديويد
Why?
را؟
Bye, bye.
باي باي
...Mengele?
مينل؟
That was David, he's off to New York for his sister's wedding,
اون ديويد بود که واسه عروسي خواهرش مرخصي رفته و داره ميره نيويورک
but he'll be back in a week.
ولي يک هفته ديه برمي رده
Mengele...
مينل
gives babies,
به ها رو ميده
fourteen years later he kills the fathers,
هارده سال بعد درها رو ميکشه
he kills Doring, Harrington, Curry.
دورين,هرينتون و کري هم ميکشه
And the Currys got their baby four weeks apart
و خانواده کري 4 هفته قبل به رو مي يرن
and the fathers were killed four weeks apart.
درها هم 4 هفته قبل از اون کشته ميشن
Wheelock.
ويلاک
Malone's dog was born December eleventh, ten weeks.
س مالوني 11 دسامبر به دنيا اومده بود و 10 هفته داشت
I've already worked it out, February the twentieth.
من قبلا حساب کردم.ميشه 20 فوريه
That's only four days from now!
که از امروز 4 روز مونده به 20 فوريه
Wheelock, New Providence, Pennsylvania.
ويلاک...روويدنس جديد,نسيلوانيا
How can I call Wheelock and tell him
طور ميتونم به ويلاک خبر بدم؟
he's going to be killed by the people who gave him his baby?
او قراره توسط کساني که به رو بهش دادن کشته بشه
That Josef Mengele has already killed the fathers of at least
جوزف مينل تا الان حداقل در
two other boys who happen to be twins?
دو تا به هايي که دوقلو بودن رو کشته
Who would believe such a preposterous story?
کي اين داستان نامعقول رو باور مي کنه؟
Herr Doktor, how kind of you to come.
دکتر خيلي لطف کرديد اومديد
A pleasure to be here.
باعث افتخار منه اينجا هستم
- Can this be little Elsa? - Yes! You remember!
اين بايد السا کوولو باشه بله...يادتونه؟
Last time I saw you were that high. You had whooping cough.
آخرين باري که ديدمت اين اندازه بودي زياد سرفه مي کردي
No, no.
نه...نه
I'm going to dance with your beautiful daughter.
ميخوام با دختر زيباتون برقصم
Good evening, how are you?
عصر بخير.حالتون طوره؟
May I present to you my wife Gertrud?
ممکنه همسرم رتراد رو معرفي کنم؟
- My love, Herr Mengele. - It's such an honour meeting you.
عشق من...مينل عزيز افتخار بزريه که شما رو ملاقات مي کنم
We're here on a little second honey-moon.
ما براي دومين ماه عسل کوتاهمون اينجا هستيم
You're supposed to be in Krintianstad, getting ready to kill Oscarsson.
شما قرار بود توي کرينستيانسان باشيد و براي کشتن اسکارسون آماده بشيد
Traitor!
خائن
No!
نه
He betrayed me!
او به من خيانت کرد
He betrayed you!
او به شما خيانت کرد
He betrayed the Aryan race!
او به نژاد آريايي خيانت کرد
Get a doctor!
يه دکتر بياريد
I am a doctor, idiot.
من يه دکترم احمق
Don't you come near him!
تو نزديک اون نشو
Shut up, you ugly bitch!
خفه شو جنده بد قيافه
- I thought you knew... - Hold still, hold still.
فکر کردم شما  ميدونيد صبر کن...صبرکن
Doktor Mengele.
دکتر مينل
Could I call you away from surgery for one moment?
ممکنه يه لحظه شما از اتاق جراحي بيرون بريد؟
If you'll excuse me.
با عرض معذرت
And why was I not told that, that man was called back?
را کسي به من نفت که اون مرد فراخواني شده؟
- All the men have been recalled. - Recalled?
تمام افراد فراخواني شدند فراخواني شدند؟
They should all be back here by the end of the week.
همشون تا آخر هفته بايد برردن
But why?
را ؟
What has happened?
مه ي شده؟
Lieberman visited Frieda Maloney in prison.
ليبر من خانم مالوني رو توي زندان ملاقات کرده
Lieberman again?
باز هم ليبرمن؟
Will I be plagued to my dying day by that infernal Jew?
از دست اين يهودي شرور دارم مي ميرم
Maloney told him about the adoptions.
مالوني درباره سر خوانده ها بهش فت
Well, that's not catastrophic, Seibert.
خوب اين که فاجعه انيز نيست سايبر
She only knows about America, work can still continue in Europe.
اون فقط در مورد کار توي آمريکا ميدونه کار ما در اروا هنوز ادامه داره
The organization doesn't share your optimism, Herr Doktor.
سازمان اين خوش بيني شما رو تقسيم نميکنه
But all Lieberman has are a few paltry shreds of information
تمام يزي که ليبرمن داره يه مشت اطلاعات آشغال بي ارزشه
that he could not possibly piece together.
كه حتي نميتونه كنار هم بذاره
Eighteen of your subjects have died.
هجده نفر از موارد مردند
That means according to your figures that we can be sure of one,
يعني با توجه به حدسيات شما ما ميتونيم از يك و يا
perhaps even two successes.
دو نفر مطمئن باشيم
And if my calculations are wrong?
آيا محاسباتم درسته؟
There's only one chance in twenty, or thirty.
تنها يك شانس هست كه به 20 نفر و يا 30 نفر برسيم
No, Seibert, the men must go back.
نه سايبرت .مردها بايد برردند
They can't, the operation has been terminated.
اونها نمي توانند.عمليات بايد متوقف بشه
Terminated?
متوقف بشه؟
By whose authority?
با اجازه كي؟
General Rausch and the Colonels.
ژنرال راش و سرهنها
I told you.
من به شما فتم
I told you from the beginning.
من از اول به شما فتم
Kill him. Kill him!
بكشش
It would have been so easy!
خيلي ساده بود
It's gone beyond Lieberman, we don't know who else is involved.
او از ليبرمن فراتر رفت ما نميدونيم ه كس ديري درير موضوع هست
You have betrayed me!
شما به من خيانت كرديد
You're all... all a bunch of selfish old men who've lost your courage.
شما همتون....همتون يه مشت آدم ير خودخواه هستيد كه شجاعت رو از دست داديد
You only want to bask in the sun in your old age!
شما توي اين سن و سال فقط ميخواهيد زير آفتاب دراز بكشيد
And if your Aryan grandchildren have to live in a world which is run
و ار نوه هاي آريايي شما قرار باشه توي دنيايي زندي کنند که توسط يهوديها و
by Jews, and Blacks, and Orientals, and slobs! You could not care less!
سياهوستها و آسياييها و کثافتها اداره ميشه شما نميتونيد بي اهميت باشيد
Your operation has been cancelled.
عمليات شما لغو شد
No!
نه
Mine continues.
مال من هنوز ادامه داره
Heil Hitler.
هاي هيتلر
This Mengele was sort of a primitive geneticist in his ons way, wasn't he?
اين مينل در مسير کارش يه جور نسل شناس قديميه
I understand that he experimented on human beings.
ميدونم که آزمايشاتي بر روي نسل بشريت انجام داده
Twins.
دوقلوها
Then he was nothing more than a sadist really.
اما اون يزي جز يک انسان ساديسمي نيست
A sadis with a M.D. And a Ph.D.
يه ساديسمي داراي مدارک"ام دي" و "ي ا دي
Well, some people would say that's a perfect definition of a scientist.
خوب بعضي از مردم مين که نمونه کامل يک دانشمنده
What exactly do you mean when you say the boys you saw
دقيقا منظورت يه که ميي سرهايي که ديدي
were more than twins?
از دوقلو بيشتر بودند؟
Not only do they look alike,
نه تنها اونها شبيه هم بودن ,بلکه
buy they were also very alike in personality.
از لحاظ شخصيتي هم شبيه هم بودن
That is unusual.
اين غير طبيعيه
Studies show that twins who are separated at birth
تحقيقات نشون داده که به هايي که از کودکي از هم جدا ميشن
develop totally different personalities.
داراي شخصيتهاي متفاوتي ميشن
But these twins, or perhaps I should say triplets
اما اين دوقلوها و شايد هم بايد بم سه قلوها
because I believe that my associate saw another
ون من باور دارم که همکارم يکي ديه از اونها رو ديده
were like the same people,
که شبيه اونها بوده
but brought up with different languages.
ولي زبان اونها با هم فرق داشته
It's impossible, of course.
اين غيرممکنه قطعا
Excuse me doctor, but what is impossible?
ببخشيد دکتر...اما ي غيرممکنه؟
What is impossible, doctor?
ه يز غيرممکنه دکتر؟
Mononuclear reproduction.
تکثير سلول تک هسته اي
Doctor.
دکتر
Cloning.
تقسيم سلولي
What if I were to tell you that I could take a scraping of skin
ي فکر مي کنيد ار به شما بم من يک تکه از وست انشت شما
from you finger and create another Ezra Lieberman?
رو برميدارم و توسط اون يک ازرا ليبرمن ديري خلق مي کنم؟
I would tell you not to waste your time, or my finger.
من به شما ميم وقت خودتون و انشت من رو تلف نکنيد
Anyway, that is cloning.
به هرحال اين تقسيم سلولي هست
It was first done with plants.
اولين بار بر روي ياهان انجام شد
A cutting taken from a plant and transplanted
يک تکه از يک ياه بريده شد و در جاي دير کاشته شد
grew to be the exact duplicate of the donor plant.
ياه رشد کرد و دقيقا مشابه ياه مولد شد
Now we are doing the same thing with laboratory animals.
ما حالا همين کارها رو بر روي حيوانات آزمايشاهي انجام ميديم
You mean, you can produce an animal from itself?
منظورتون اينه که شما از يک حيوان ميتونيد يک حيوان ديه توليد کنيد؟
We take the unfertilized egg off an ovulating female
ما تخمک بارور نشده رو از زن تخمک ذار مي يريم
and destroy all of its genes and chromosomes.
و تمام ژنها و کروموزومها رو نابود مي کنيم
We then implant the nucleus of the donor cell
سس  ما هسته سلول بنيادي رو که
which could be taken from a blood sample, or even a skin scraping.
ميتونه از يک نمونه خون و يا حتي يک تکه از وست رفته شده باشه رو ميکاريم
That cell with its genetic material intact,
سلول با مواد سالم ژنتيکي دست نخورده و سالم
eventually becomes an embryo and is born as a living creature.
سرانجام تبديل به جنين شده و يک موجود زنده توليد ميشه
Without parents?
بدون در و مادر؟
Well, it has no father because the egg was never fertilized.
خوب....دري وجود نداره ون تخمک از ابتدا بارور نبوده
No mother, because its genetic code comes from another being.
مادر هم نداره...ون شناسه ژنتيکي از جاي ديري هست
Can you follow that?
متوجه ميشيد؟
And this creature, is an exact duplicate of itself?
و اين موجود دقيقا يک مخلوق ساخته شده از خودشه
Doctor, how can that be?
دکتر طور نين يزي ممکنه؟
Come along.
بياييد
Ous experiments began with the simplest of animals,
آزمايشات ما ابتدا بر روي ساده ترين حيوانات انجام شد
shrimps and frogs.
ميوها و قورباغه ها
Animals in which the female's eggs are fertilized externally.
حيواناتي که تخمک اونها توسط لقاح خارجي بارور ميشه
Then we moved on to mammals.
بعد به سراغ ستانداران رفتيم
We tried several laboratoty animals
بر روي حيوانات آزمايشاهي مختلفي آزمايش کرديم
and found the rabbit most convenient.
و فهميديم خروش از همه مناسب تره
I had to develop instruments which could accomplig the operation
من مي بايست وسايل رو تکميل مي کردم که عمليات انجام بشه
and a whole micro-injection system
و يک سيستم تزريق ميکروسکوي نياز داشتم
I'll show you how it's done.
بهتون نشون ميدم طوري انجام شد
Here we are removing the eggs of white rabbit from the Fallopian tubes.
اينجا ما تخمک خروش سفيد رو از درون لوله هاي فالو بيرون مياريم
Now, you see the egg under a microscope.
حالا شما تخمک رو زير ميکروسکو مي بينيد
I've brought the point of an ordinary sewing needle into view
من يک سوزن خياطي معمولي هم آوردم که ببينيد
to give an idea of the size.
که بتونيد اندازه رو مقايسه کنيد
They are that small?
اينقدر کوک هستن؟
Most mammal eggs are about that size.
تخمک اغلب ستانداران همين اندازه هست
- Including human eggs? - Yes.
تخمک انسان هم همين اندازه است؟ بله
The next step is to destroy the egg nucleus
مرحله بعدي از بين بردن هسته تخمک
with ultraviolet light.
به وسيله نور فرابنفشه
So that none of its genetic make-up remains.
طوريکه هي کدام از خواص ژنتيکي باقي نمونه
Now you see an egg from a white rabbit
حالا شما يک تخمک از يک خروش سفيد مي بينيد
ready to be injected with the blood cell from a black rabbit donor.
که براي تزريق يک سلول خوني از خروش سياه آماده هست
With the injection pipette one of the blood cells is sucked up
به وسيله يت تزريق يکي از سلولهاي خوني بالا کشيده ميشه
and then injected into the egg.
و به درون تخمک تزريق ميشه
After a few hours the eggs in culture divide
بعد از ند ساعت تخمکها جدا مي شوند
and are ready to be put back into the female.
و آماده براي کاشتن در رحم مادر
There, they grow into embryos,
اونجا رشد کرده و تبديل به جنين مي شوند
which in a month's time the normal gestation period,
و در مدت يک ماه,دوره معمول بارداري
they will become baby rabbits.
اونها تبديل به به خروش ميشن
In this instance, a black litter, from a a white mother
که در اين مورد يک مادر سفيد به سياه  به دنيا مياره
and their black colour proves that they have been cloned
و رن سياهش ثابت ميکنه که از
from the blood cell of a black rabbit.
سلول خوني يک خروش سياه توليد شده
But, isn't it difficult to get the egg back into the female?
اما بررداندن تخمک توي رحم مادر مشکل نيست؟
Transferring the eggs isn't a problem
انتقال تخمک کار سختي نيست
we do that all the time with laboratory animals.
ما هميشه اين کار رو با حيوانات آزمايشاهي انجام ميديم
The really tricky part is the micro-surgery.
قسمت واقعا حساس اين فرايند
Getting the donor cell into the egg.
تزريق سلول به درون تخمک هست
You're lucky if one in ten survives.
اه خوش شانس باشيد يک دهم اونها زنده ميمونن
This can be done with humans?
اين براي انسانها قابل اجرا هست؟
If the surgical technique were precise enough.
اه تکنيکهاي جراحي به اندازه کافي دقيق باشن
- It's monstrous, doctor! - Why?
اين وحشتناکه دکتر را؟
Wouldn't you want to live in a world full of Mozarts and Picassos?
شما دوست نداري توي دنيايي که ر از موزارت و يکاسو هست زندي کني؟
Of course, it's only a dream.
قطعا اين فقط يک رويا هست
Not only would you have to reproduce the genetic code of the donor,
نه تنها مي بايست خواص ژنتيکي انتقال يافته رو تکثير کرد بلکه
but the environmental background as well.
يشينه زيست محيطي را هم به همان خوبي بايد تکثير کرد
Is Mengele trying to reproduce himself?
آيا مينل ميخواد يکي مثل خودش رو توليد کنه؟
No, he has brown eyes, and he comes from a very wealthy family.
نه...اون شمان قهوه اي داره و از يک خانواده خيلي ثروتمند اومده
Let's examine the family background of the donor.
بياييد انتقال دهنده وراثتيش رو بررسي کنيم
The father is sixty-five years old.
در 65 ساله
Civil servant.
استخدام غير نظامي
The mother is forty-two, you say?
مادر 42 ساله ...درسته؟
She dotes on the child.
عاشق به
The boy is...
سره
pale...
رن ريده
dark hair...
موهاي تيره
blue eyes.
شمان آبي
Right?
درسته؟
Now, Mengele would certainly know every social and environmental detail
حال مينل بايد تمام خصوصيات اجتماعي و محيطي
would have to be reproduced.
رو که قراره تکثير بشه بدونه
Thus, if the parents were divorced when the boy was ten,
س ار والدينش زماني که اون 10ساله بود طلاق رفته باشن
this would have to be arranged.
اين ميتونه برنامه ريزي شده باشه
Doctor Bruckner,
دکتر بروکنر
the one who is cloned,
کسي که تقسيم سلولي کرده
the donor,
از انتقال دهنده
- he has to be alive, doesn't he? - Not necessarily.
اون بايد زنده باشه.مه نه؟ الزاما نه
Individual cells taken from a donor can be preserved indefinitely.
سلولهاي فردي دريافت شده را ميشه به مدت نامحدود نهداري کرد
With a sample of Mozart's blood and the women,
با يک نمونه خوني از موزارت و ند تا زن
someone with the skill and the equipment,
يه نفر با داشتن مهارت و تجهيزات
could breed a few hundred baby Mozarts.
ميتونست ند صد تا به موزارت توليد کنه
My God.
خداي من
If it's really been done,
ار اين واقعا انجام ميشد
what I'd give to see one of those boys.
ي بايد بدم که بتونم يکي از اون به ها رو ببينم؟
Herr Lieberman!
آقاي ليبرمن
Not Mozart, doctor.
نه موزارت دکتر
Not Picasso.
نه يکاسو
Not a genius who would enrich the world,
نه يک نابغه که جهان رو ر از نبوغش کنه
but a lonely little boy
فقط يک سر کوک تنها
with a domineering father,
با يک در مستبد
a customs officer
يک افسر مرک
who was fifty-two when he was born.
که وقتي به دنيا اومد نجاه و دو سال داشت
And...
و
an affectionate doting mother
و يک مادر دلسوز
who was twenty-nine.
که 29 ساله بود
The father died at sixty-five
در در سن 65 سالي مرد
when the boy was nearly fourteen.
زماني که سر تقريبا 14 ساله بود
Adolf Hitler.
آدولف هيتلر
Colonel Seibert.
سرهن سايبرت
You Lieberman?
تويي ليبرمن؟
Ja.
آره
Come in.
بيا داخل
Okay, boys.
باشه سرها
Beautiful dogs.
سهاي زيبايي هستند
Tear the throat out of anyone who even looks cross-eyed at me.
لوي هرکسي رو که به من ناه  بکنه اره مي کنند
I guess you can see why I didn't exactly wet my pants
حدس ميزنم متوجه شديد که را من از ترس شلوارم رو خيس نکردم
when you said someone was out to get me.
وقتي که فتيد يه نفر بيرون ميخواد منو بيره
Yeah.
بله
Take off your coat.
کتت رو دربيار
Very impressive.
خيلي يرا
Yeah.
بله
My son took those pictures.
سرم اون عکسها رو رفته
Very good.
خيلي خوبه
A little artsy-fartsy, if you ask me.
يه کوولوي هنرمنده ار نظرم رو بخواي
- Is your son at home now? - No, he's in school.
سرتون الان خونه هست؟ نه مدرسه هست
And Mrs. Wheelock, is she at home?
و خانم ويلاک طور؟ اون خونه هست؟
She's still at work.
اون هنوز سر کاره
So you're the guy who got that Nazi Eichmann?
س تو اون شخصي هستي که نازي ايمن رو رفت؟
I located him.
من جاش رو يدا کردم
It was the Israelis who did the actual kidnapping.
اسرائيليها بودن که آدم ربايي واقعي رو انجام دادن
How much did you get for that?
واسه اين کار قدر ول رفتي؟
Nothing.
هيي
I did it for the satisfaction, I hate all Nazis.
واسه رضاي خودم انجام دادم من از نازيها متنفرم
I don't know about the Nazis.
من در مورد نازيها يزي نميدونم
The Niggers we got to worry about.
به اندازه کافي نراني داريم
Hey, why are these Nazis after me?
هي... را اين نازيها دنبال من هستن؟
Well...
خوب
You know, I...
ميدوني...من
I find it very hard to talk.
خيلي سخته که بخوام صحبت کنم
Don't worry about them, they won't bother you
نران اونها نباش اونها تو رو اذيت نمي کنن
unless you bother me.
مر اينکه منو اذيت کني
I was attacked by... by a dog when I was a child,
من وقتي به بودم يه س به من حمله کرد
a German shepherd,
يک جرمن شيفرد
and I still feel uncomfortable with a dog in the room.
و هنوز هم با سها توي يک اتاق احساس راحتي نمي کنم
Jesus! You're like my neighbour Wally.
خدايا...تو شبيه همسايه من والي هستي
I mean, he won't even walk up the driveway
يعني ار سها بسته نباشن
unless the dogs are lockep up.
حتي از توي جاده هم رد نميشه
Okay.
خوب
Come on, boys, in you go.
بيايد به ها بريد داخل
There's no other way that they can come in?
راه ديري وجود نداره که بتونن وارد بشن؟
No.
نه
Thank you.
ممنونم
I feel much better.
خيلي بهتر شد
Hey!
هي
Put your hands up.
دستها بالا
What the hell are you up to, anyway?
بالاخره تو ه کاره هستي؟
Is there a basement in this house?
اين خونه زيرزمين داره؟
Yeah.
بله
Take me to it.
منو ببر اونجا
Do you have any pictures of your son?
عکسي از سرت داري؟
There's an album on the table.
روي ميز يه دونه آلبوم هست
What do you want them for?
اونها رو واسه ي ميخواي؟
Please, do not worry.
لطفا نران نباش
I am very anxious to see him and talk to him.
من خيلي مشتاقم ببينمش و باهاش صحبت کنم
I am the doctor who delivered him.
من دکتري هستم که اون رو تحويل دادم
Open the door.
در رو باز کن
Go down the stairs, Mr. Wheelock.
برو از له ها ايين آقاي ويلاک
Now, listen, I don't give a doodily-shit about Jews or Nazis.
حالا وش کن...من به اندازه ه واسه يهودي يا نازي ارزش قائل نيستم
Good.
خوبه
Tell me, please, which way to Quarryville?
بو لطفا از کدوم سمت به کواري ويلي ميشه رفت؟
Turn left at the end of the exit,
به انتهاي خروجي که رسيدي برو سمت
it's beyond Thirty, take a left, it'll take you straight into Quarryville.
بيش از 30 تا که رفتي برو و مستقيم ميرسي به کواري ويلي
Thank you.
متشکرم
Quiet, damn you!
آروم باش لعنت به تو
Bobby, dear, dear, boy.
بابي...عزيزم...عزيزم...سر
Mr. Wheelock.
آقاي ويلاک
Mister...
آقا
You.
تو
Herr Lieberman.
ليبرمن
Get up, Jew!
بلند شو يهودي
Up!
بالا
Yes, I am going to kill you,
بله...ميخوام تو رو بکشم
but I want you to go to your death with the knowledge
ولي من ميخوام شما با اين آاهي بميريد که
that all your efforts have gone for nothing!
تمام تلاش شما بيهوده بود
I have the money, and I have the will!
من ول رو دارم و وصيت نامه رو هم دارم
And no one can stop me!
و کسي نميتونه جلوي من رو بيره
Did you kill Wheelock?
تو ويلاک رو کشتي؟
No, he's in the kitchen, mixing us some cocktails.
نه ...اون توي آشزخانه داره براي ما نوشيدني آماده ميکنه
Do you know what I saw on the television in my motel room
ميدوني امروز صبح ساعت 1 توي اتاقم
at one o'clock this morning?
در هتل از تلويزيون ي ديدم؟
Films of Hitler.
فيلمهاي هيتلر
They are showing films about the war,
داشتند فيلمهايي از جن رو خش مي کردن
the movement, people are fascinated,
تحرک...مردم شيفته شده بودن
the time is ripe.
زمان فرا رسيده
Adolf Hitler is alive.
آدولف هيتلر زنده هست
Tis album is full of pictures of him.
اين آلبوم ر از عکسهاي اونه
Bobby Wheelock and ninety-three other boys
بابي ويلاک و 93 سر ديه
are exact genetic duplicates of him.
دقيقا همزاد ژنتيکي اون هستن
Bred entirely from his cells.
کاملا از سلولهاي او به وجود اومدن
He allowed me to take half a litre of his blood
او به من اجازه داد که نيم ليتر از خونش رو بردارم
and a cutting of skin from his ribs.
و يک تکه از وست بدنش
We were in a biblical frame of mind.
ما درون قاب مقدس ذهن بوديم
On the 23rd of May, 1943, at the Berghof.
در 23 مي 1943 در برهوف
He had denied himself children because he knew that no son
او به هاي خودش رو رد کرد.ون ميدونست
could flourish in the shadow of so God-like a father.
نميتونن در سايه همين خدايي شکوفا بشن مانند يک در
But then he heard what was theoretically possible
ولي او به طور نظري فهميد که ه يزي ممکنه
that I could create one day not his son not even a carbon copy,
که من ميتونستم نه سرش رو و نه يک کي از اون رو بلکه يک
but another original!
اصل ديري از اون رو خلق کنم
He was thrilled by the idea!
او از اين ايده وحشت کرد
The right Hitler for the right future.
هيتلر واقعي براي آينده واقعي
A Hitler tailor-made for the 1980's, '90's, 2000.
يک هيتلر مناسب براي 1980 و 1990 و 2000
Kill!
بکشيدش
Away!
م شو
Off!
خفه
No more gun.
اسلحه نداري؟
Holy shit!
اي واي
Bobby.
بابي
My dear, dear boy.
سر عزيز عزيز من
You cannot possibly imagine how happy I am,
نميتوني تصور کني قدر خوشحالم
how joyous I am, to see you standing there so fine, strong and handsome.
قدر خوشحالم از اينکه تو رو اينجا مي بينم که سالم و قوي و خوش تي ايستادي
Call these dogs off, Bobby, call the dogs off, please.
اين سها رو دور کن بابي...سها رو دور کن لطفا
I'm an old friend of the family.
من يه دوست قديمي خانوادي هستم
In fact I'm the doctor who delivered you.
در واقع من دکتري هستم که تو رو تحويل دادم
And I stopped by, having just returned from abroad,
و  همين حالا از خارج کشور برشتم
and he let me in.
و اون ذاشت بيام داخل
And then he pulled out a gun,
و بعدش يه اسلحه در آورد
fortunately I was able to overpower him.
خوشبختانه تونستم از سش بربيام
Now call them off, Bobby, call them off, please.
حالا لطفا اينها رو ببر....ببرشون بابي
Cut!
بسه
Cut, how clever.
بسه...ه باهوش
I said, 'off', and I said, 'away' and I said 'no gun, no more gun'.
من فتم م شو...من فتم...خفه.....فتم تفن ندارم ديه تفن ندارم
- Then you had the gun. - No, he had, he...
س تو تفن داشتي....نه اون داشت
They're trained to attack anyone carrying a gun.
اونها آموزش ديدن به کسي که تفن داره حمله کنن
- They were locked up and let them out. - The dogs are never locked up.
اونها ير افتاده بودن....اون در رو واسشون باز کرد اونها هي وقت ير نمي فتند
Bobby.
بابي
- My dear, dear... - Action!
عزيز عزيز.....حمله
Cut. Cut!
بسه
They won't listen to you.
اونها که به تو وش نميدن
Bobby.
بابي
That man is your enemy, don't listen to him, I beg of you.
اون مرد دشمن توهست.به حرفش وش نده .التماست ميکنم
Call the police.
به ليس زن بزن
Yeah.
آره
By all means, do so, Bobby,
کاري که لازمه انجام بده بابي
but first there are some things about yourself you must know.
اما اول يه يزهايي در مورد خودت هست که بايد بدوني
What do you mean?
منظورت يه؟
If I prove to you that I know you better than anyone in the world,
ار به تو ثابت کنم که من تو رو از هر کسي تو دنيا بهتر مي شناسم
better even than your own mother, will you listen to me?
حتي بهتر از مادر خودت , اون وقت به حرفم وش ميدي؟
You are a clever boy.
تو سر باهوشي هستي
Are you not?
مه نيستي؟
You do not do well in school, that is because you are too clever.
زباد تو مدرسه خوب نبودي ون تو باهوش هستي
Too busy thinking your own thoughts,
خيلي به خودت فکر ميکني
but you are much smarter than your teachers, eh?
اما تو خيلي از معلمهات باهوشتر هستي ها؟
My teachers are nowhere.
معلمهاي من اينجا نيستن
You are going to be the world's greatest photographer, are you not?
تو قراره که بزرترين عکاس جهان بشي.مه نه؟
Have you ever felt superior to those around you?
آيا تا حالا نسبت به اطرافيانت احساس برتري کردي؟
Like a prince among peasants?
مثل يه شاهزاده در ميان دهاتي ها؟
I feel different from everyone sometimes.
من احساس ميکنم با همه فرق دارم بعضي وقتها
You are infinitely different.
تو قطعا فرق داري
Infinitely superior.
قطعا برتر هستي
You were born of the noblest blood in the world.
تو از اصيل ترين خون جهان به وجود اومدي
You have it within you to fulfil ambitions
تو خوني رو درونت داري که سرشار از جاه طلبي هست
a thousand times greater than those of which you presently dream.
هزار بار بيشتر از اون يزي که تو تا الان تو خواب ميديدي
And you shall fulfil them, Bobby.
و تو بايد بيشترش کني بابي
You shall.
بايد
You are the living duplicate of the greatest man
تو همزاد زنده بزرترين مرد
in history.
تاريخ هستي
Adolf Hitler.
آدولف هيتلر
Oh, man, you're weird.
اوه تو خارق العاده اي
Bobby, I'm telling you the truth.
بابي من دارم حقيقت رو بهت ميم
- Find your father. - What?
درت رو يدا کن ي؟
He killed your father.
او درت رو کشت
Bobby, listen to me.
بابي به من وش بده
It was this vicious Jew, your sworn enemy.
اين يهودي بدکاره دشمن تو هست
He killed your father, and he came here to kill you.
او درت رو کشت و اومد اينجا که تو رو بکشه
Bobby.
بابي
Let me protect you.
بذار ازت محافظت کنم
All your power will burst forth when the time comes.
تمام قدرت تو وقتي زمانش برسه از هم مي اشه
When you grow older
وقتي که بزرتر ميشي
and you see the world engulfed by human garbage.
و مي بيني که جهان به وسيله آشغالهاي انسان به لجن کشيده شده
When you feel this urge rising within you to save your own Aryan folk
وقتي ديدي اين احساس همراه تو داره رشد ميکنه قوم آريايي رو از
from extintion.
انقراض نجات بده
Then you will rejoice in your heritage
اونوقت ميتوني از ميراثت لذت ببري
and bless me for creating you.
و از من بخاطر خلق تو تشکر کني
Bobby!
بابي
You must understand! Your parents are of no importance!
تو بايد بفهمي والدينت مهم نبودند
They were chosen for you!
اونها براي تو انتخاب شده بودند
Now that they have served their purpose
حالا که نتيجه کارشون رو دادند
they must disappear from your life!
بايد از زندي تو ناديد بشن
Bobby!
بابي
You freaked-out maniac!
تو رواني ترسو هستي
Bite!
ازش بير
Bobby!
بابي
Holy shit!
لعنتي
Cut.
بسه
Hey, man!
هي مرد
Get out of here!
از اينجا برو بيرون
Out.
بيرون
I think you'll die if I don't call an ambulance for you.
فکر کنم ار واست آمبولانس نيرم اينجا مي ميري
I could just go out right now,
من الان فقط ميتونم برم بيرون
my mum won't be home until late.
مادرم تا دير وقت خونه نمياد
You'll be dead by then.
تا اون موقع تو مي ميري
If I call the police, will you tell them what I did?
ار به ليس زن بزنم بهشون ميي من ه کاري کرم؟
Okay.
باشه
Shake.
دست بده
Come on, shake.
زود باش دست بده
Okay, you got a deal.
خوبه تو قول دادي
I'd like an ambulance and a police car to the Wheelock residence
من يک آمبولانس و يک ماشين ليس ميخوام توي محل اقامت آقاي ويلاک
on Old Buck Road, please.
جاده اولد باک لطفا
Hey, man, this is an emergency.
هي آقا اين يه مورد اضطراريه
A heavy duty emergency.
اضطراري خيلي شديد
David.
ديويد
What a surprise.
سوررايز ي هست؟
Which one of the assassins was it, Mr. Lieberman?
کدو بک از قاتلها بود آقاي ليبرمن؟
I thought you went to a wedding.
من فکر کردم رفتي عروسي
No more deception now.
ديه حقه نيست
No more blind alleys.
ديه کور بودن نيست
All right.
باشه
It was Mengele.
مينل بود
He's dead.
او مرده
It's over.
تمام شد
The Doring boy ins't dead yet.
سر به هنوز زنده هست
Neither is Simon Harrington, nor Jack Curry or Bobby Wheelock.
و سيمون هرينتون و جک هاري و بابي ويلاک زنه هستند
It took a little time, a little back tracking,
يه کم زمان ميبره ...يه کم بازبيني ميخواد
a visit to Dr. Bruckner.
يه ملاقات با دکتر بروکنر
But now we know...
ولي حالا همه يز رو
everything.
ميدونيم
And what are you going to do about it?
حالا ميخواي با اين ه کار کني؟
Kill the boys.
سرها رو بکشيد
Brilliant man that Mengele.
مينل مرد درخشان
I suppose he had all 94 of those names and addresses memorized.
فکر ميکنم اون تمام 94 تا اسم و آرسهاشون رو حفظ بود
Now, you are trying to fool me.
حالا تو داري سعي ميکني من رو خر کني
You have been searching the room.
You have been searching the room.
- He must've had a list. - He did, now I have it.
- He must've had a list. - He did, now I have it.
Give it to me.
Give it to me.
Why?
Why?
We have the right and we have the duty.
We have the right and we have the duty.
To do what? Kill children?
To do what? Kill children?
Give me that list.
Give me that list.
You'll have to take it from me.
You'll have to take it from me.
And when you do you can add my name to the list.
And when you do you can add my name to the list.
I don't mean you any harm.
I don't mean you any harm.
You'll have to kill me, David.
You'll have to kill me, David.
The first of those boys that you touch,
The first of those boys that you touch,
I will turn you and your entire organization over to the police.
I will turn you and your entire organization over to the police.
I swear I'll do that.
I swear I'll do that.
You would protect Hitler?
You would protect Hitler?
No.
No.
Not... not slaughter the innocnet, and neither will you.
Not... not slaughter the innocnet, and neither will you.
A fanatic you may be, but a murderer of young children you are not.
A fanatic you may be, but a murderer of young children you are not.
You know, there is a nurse here,
You know, there is a nurse here,
an angel of mercy called Miss Hanrahan,
an angel of mercy called Miss Hanrahan,
who actually gives me cigarettes.
who actually gives me cigarettes.
You know, what she said to me the other day?
You know, what she said to me the other day?
She said, 'Mr. Lieberman, if you can escape Buchenwald
She said, 'Mr. Lieberman, if you can escape Buchenwald
and you can escape those bullets, then a few cigarettes will not hurt you.'
and you can escape those bullets, then a few cigarettes will not hurt you.'
Wasn't that a nice thing to say?
Wasn't that a nice thing to say?
Mad.
Mad.